hey push students let's cover everything
you need for period
[Music]
5 before we start print out the free
speed review sheet that goes along with
this video the link is in the
description below go ahead and look at
period 5 Circle any people events or
vocab that you don't quite remember so
you know what you need to study then
once you're confident you've mastered a
topic you can check it off and move on
to the next one all right here we go
period 5 starts with Manifest Destiny
coined by journalist John O Sullivan was
the idea that it was America's god-given
duty to expand across the rest of the
this was promoted by James K pulk the
Manifest Destiny president in his 1844
election he campaigned on the Logan 544
or fight declaring that America would
gain the orgon territory from Britain
the discovery of gold in California in
1848 also fueled this idea many
Americans were willing to risk the
hardships found along the westward
Trails like the Oregon Santa Fe and
Mormon and hopes of a brighter future
and economic opportunities out west
following Texas Independence debates
increased over annexation Texas wanted
to be admitted into the Union but
Congress worried that it would upset the
balance between slave and free states
that had been established since the
Missouri Compromise But ultimately Texas
was annexed in 1845 by President pul
shortly after there was a border dispute
between America and Mexico at the Rio
grun River Fighting broke out leading to
the Mexican-American War during the war
Pennsylvania representative David Wilmot
proposed that the institution of slavery
be banned from any land gained as a
result of the war even though this
proposal failed it demonstrated sexual
tensions of the time and it increased
Southern fears that the government was
trying to abolish slavery the war
officially ended in 18 1948 with the
Treaty of guadal Lupa Dogo which
significantly extended American land
America's borders were extended West to
the Pacific Ocean and South to the Rio
Grand River although the southern border
wasn't finalized until the gadston
purchase following the Mexican session
tension increased over the status of the
new land would slavery be permitted many
Americans like the Free Soil Party
wanted to prevent slavery from expanding
into the new territories but the
southerners were willing to protect it
at all costs this led Henry Clay to
negotiate the Compromise of 1850 while
it added California as a free state it
allowed for popular sovereignty in Utah
and New Mexico and even though the
compromise banned the slave trade in
Washington DC it strengthened the
Fugitive Slave wall this angered
Northerners because they felt it made
them complicit in the institution of
slavery tensions reached a boiling point
in 1854 with the passage of the Kansas
Nebraska Act because it allowed for
popular sovereignty in the two
territories it nullified the 3630 line
established under the Missouri
Compromise both Pro and anti-slavery
factions flooded into the territory
hoping to influence the vote leading to
bleeding Kansas this led to the
formation of the Republican Party who
were able to unify Americans who opposed
the expansion of slavery into the
western territories as tension over
slavery increased abolitionists began
taking action period Tubman helped an
estimated 300 slaves escaped to the
north on the Underground Railroad and
Harriet beer Stow published her novel
Uncle Tom's Cabin which showed the
cruelty and inhumanity of enslavement
but many Southerners continued to defend
the institution of slavery like George
fitzu he argued that the working
condition and treatment of Northern
Industrial laborers was worse than
slavery in the 1857 Dread Scott Case The
Supreme Court declared that
African-Americans were not citizens and
therefore could not Sue in a US court
this decision effectively declared the
Missouri Compromise unconstitutional
which was a major setback for the
Abolitionist cause and some
abolitionists like John Brown used more
extreme tactics Brown led the raid on
Harper's fery Virginia in an attempt to
arm a slave rebellion while some viewed
Brown as a martyr after this it
increased Southern fear that the north
might resort to violence to end the
institution of slavery and while the
North had a diverse economy based on
manufacturing and trade the Southern
economy almost exclusively relied on
Plantation agriculture this made
Southerners unwilling to compromise on
the institution of slavery and they
frequently use the state's rights
argument these economic differences also
led to debates over tariffs because they
helped Northern manufacturing but hurt
Southern cotton sales but all these
tensions reached their Breaking Point
with the 1860 presidential election four
candidates ran for president including a
split Democratic ticket this enabled
Lincoln to win despite not receiving a
single Southern vote South Carolina
seceded short L after followed by six
more Southern States they formed the
Confederate States of America and
elected Mississippi's Jefferson Davis as
president of the Confederacy going into
the war the North had significant
advantages they had a larger population
control of the US Navy and the banks
which meant access to money they also
had more infrastructure like railroads
and more farmland for growing food
however the South managed to sustain the
war effort for years because of their
determination to keep slavery they also
had better military leadership with
experienced generals such as Roberty Lee
there are few key events you want to
know from the Civil War first is Fort
Sumpter the official start to the war
next is antium the Confederate loss here
discouraged for and 8 the Battle of
Gettysburg was considered the turning
point of the war and officially ended
Southern attempts to invade the north
the Atlanta Campaign is also significant
because General Sherman used Total War
to destroy the southern morale and
supplies weaving a path of Destruction
from Atlanta to Savannah and finally
aama matics where the Confederacy was
forced to surrender Lincoln's leadership
was instrumental in the victory he was
determined to restore the Union after
Fort Suter Lincoln approved the draft of
75,000 troops and as the war continued
the conscription Act was passed in 1863
to draft additional troops Lincoln also
continued the pattern of previous
Presidents by restricting civil
liberties during the war with his
suspension of habus Corpus anyone
rebelling or interfering with a war
effort could be arrested and denied
legal rights this was especially
controversial in the border states like
Maryland following the Union victory at
antium Lincoln issued the Emancipation
Proclamation freeing the enslaved from
States at open Rebellion although didn't
end all slavery in America it officially
made the war about slavery it also
allowed African-Americans to join the
Union Army four score and seven years
ago Lincoln's Infamous Gettysburg
Address also helped redefine the purpose
of the war by promoting the principles
of equality and Freedom the speech also
inspired soldiers and civilians to
continue supporting the war effort and
although Lincoln had a plan to rebuild
the union following the conclusion of
the war he was unable to implement them
because of his assassination by John
wils Booth so once the war was
officially over the government had had
the difficult task of putting the
country back together Lincoln's initial
plan was to restore the union quickly by
only requiring 10% of the state's voters
to pledge an oath of allegiance to the
union Johnson's plan required the
southern states to revoke secession and
abolish slavery but it also pardoned
many Confederate Leaders The Radical
Republicans however wanted to Grant full
citizenship and voting rights to the
Freedman and punish the former
Confederate leaders they used military
force in southern states to implement
their reconstruction policies there were
many successes During the Reconstruction
Era the formation the freedman's bureau
helped transition lives for the newly
Freedman by providing basic necessities
like food clothing and Medical Care it
also built schools the Reconstruction
amendments were ratified as well the
13th amendment abolished slavery the 14
defined citizenship and the 15th granted
Universal male suffrage regardless of
race this led to the election of many
African-Americans to public office such
as hyro Rebels despite these successes
there were many failures During the
Reconstruction Era as well many white
Southerners resisted reconstruction
measures by instituting restrictive Jim
Crow laws that legalized segregation
they also used pull taxes and literacy
tests to keep freed men from voting
there was also an increase in racial
Violence by the formation of white
supremacy groups like The K Klux Clan
ultimately reconstruction was ended with
a compromise of 1877 with a split
election the house selected Rutherford
be haaz in exchange for removing federal
troops from the south so what will this
look like on exam day for causation you
could see effects of manifest destiny
causes for the rise in anti-slavery
sentiments and causes of the Civil War
you could also see comparison questions
with the union and Confederacy including
their Regional differences and their War
strengths and strategies so remember
while the union had a larger population
and Industry the South had a strong
commitment to the Confederate cause and
for changeing continuity you're most
likely to be asked how reconstruction
changed or failed to change American
society so while there were successes
like the fredman's bureau ultimately it
failed to provide long-term protection
for African-American rights check out
the apish ultimate review packet for
more help we've got timeline study
guides and Essay practice follow the
link in the description below to get a
free preview and if you think this video
was helpful like And subscribe thanks
for
watching